<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-05-13T15:32:32+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ice-Interactions</title><subtitle>Dave Porter&apos;s Personal Research Website </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Postdoc advert (PDF)</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2022/PDRS-pdf/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Postdoc advert (PDF)"/><published>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2022/PDRS-pdf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2022/PDRS-pdf/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A longer description of our PDRS job posting.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Postdoc opening!</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2022/PDRS_search/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Postdoc opening!"/><published>2022-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-02-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2022/PDRS_search</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2022/PDRS_search/"><![CDATA[<p>Postdoc at LDEO-Columbia University working on ice shelf processes and modeling</p> <h1 id="new-job-opening">New Job Opening</h1> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/ross-ice-front_fromLC130.JPG"/><br/> (View of Ross Ice Shelf front from an LC130 from the ROSETTA-Ice survey.)</p> <p>Come work with myself and Drs. Jonny Kingslake, Kirsty Tinto, and Renata Constantino to conduct research in the field of glacier geophysics and ice sheet modeling. We will use data from NASA Operation IceBridge and ROSETTA-Ice aerogeophysical campaigns over the Ross Ice Shelf, remote sensing (e.g. satellite altimetry from ICESat-II), and numerical modeling to <strong>better understand the vulnerability of Antarctic ice shelves due to channelized melting</strong>. You wil have the opportunity to take a leading role in ice flow model development, with potential linkages to existing Pangeo projects and the NCAR climate model ecosystem.</p> <p><a href="/files/COMBINED_PDRS_description.pdf">See full job description here</a></p> <p><a href="https://academic.careers.columbia.edu/#!/92740">And apply here!</a></p> <p>Please reach out to us with any questions!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="hiring"/><category term="NASA"/><category term="Antarctica"/><category term="Aerogeophysics"/><category term="postdoc advertisement"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hiring a PDRS for our new NASA Cryo Project on aerogrephysics of ice shelf basal channels.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">WIRED: Deep Channel Under Thwaites Glacier</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/09/wired/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="WIRED: Deep Channel Under Thwaites Glacier"/><published>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-09-15T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/09/wired</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/09/wired/"><![CDATA[<p><br/><img src="/assets/img/tweet_wired.png"/><br/> (Tweet via WIRED)</p> <p>====== Check out this great WIRED article on new findings about two major vulnerabilities of Thwaites Glacier.</p> <blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr"><a href="https://t.co/gEEOcwQrh2">https://t.co/gEEOcwQrh2</a> via <a href="https://twitter.com/WIRED?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@wired</a> <br/><br/>Ice sheet melt, two ways.</p>&mdash; David Porter (@gridstorm) <a href="https://twitter.com/gridstorm/status/1305896767553245184?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 15, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Thwaites Glacier"/><category term="ITGC"/><category term="Twitter"/><category term="Airborne Gravimetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(Tweet via WIRED)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">NNA State-of-the-Planet post</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2020/blog-post-Nuuk_2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="NNA State-of-the-Planet post"/><published>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-02-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2020/blog-post-Nuuk_2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/blog/2020/blog-post-Nuuk_2/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[New post by Margie Turrin up on EI website.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Nuuk, Greenland</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/01/blog-post-Nuuk-meeting/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Nuuk, Greenland"/><published>2020-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/01/blog-post-7</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/01/blog-post-Nuuk-meeting/"><![CDATA[<p><br/><img src="/assets/img/Nuuk - 2010, January - 1 of 7.png"/><br/> (Caption: Flight into GOH)</p> <h1 id="meeting-with-new-greenland-rising-partners-in-nuuk-greenland">Meeting with new ‘Greenland Rising’ partners in Nuuk, Greenland</h1> <p>In the age of digital communication tools, such as FaceTime and Skype, it’s often easy to forget how valuable in-person interactions can be. A great way to keep up-to-date with college roommates and siblings abroad, it introduces additional stresses to burgeoning relationships (e.g. internet connection issues, microphone and speaker settings, etc.).</p> <p>Although on the whole positive experiences, our virtual meetings with our Greenlandic partners were no different, which is why we were excited to follow Karl’s advice and visit Nuuk for a ‘kick-off’ meeting - in January! I’ve been to Thule AFB in NW Greenland in late-March before, so I had experience with wintertime at high-latitudes, but that was for airborne field work and I wasn’t sure how ‘normal’ business would be carried out with bitter cold, snow and wind, and just a few hours of daylight.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/Nuuk - 2010, January - 5 of 7.png"/><br/></p> <hr/> <p>Never mind! It was fantastic! All of our new collaborators were a joy to meet, diving right in to the nitty-gritty of the project details, both broad ideas and detailed logistics. And yes the weather was fierce, but it was also fun. GINR has excellent accommodations, delicious food of both Danish and Greenlandic variety, and plenty of opportunities for exercise (groomed cross-country skiing, Greenland’s only lap swim pool, running on the roadside paths, etc.) - needless to say I had a blast and can’t wait to return!</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/NNA_workplan.png"/><br/></p> <p>Above is a quick overview of our working plan for this NNA, highlighting the three key components and the where and how they will be implemented in our four key communities.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/Nuuk - 2010, January - 7 of 7.png"/><br/> Kultarnat (Culture Night) at GINR.</p> <p>A joint US-Greenlandic team with the new <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=505594" title="NSF: NNA">tides</a> …</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Greenland"/><category term="Sea level rise"/><category term="community engagement"/><category term="Ice sheet change"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(Caption: Flight into GOH)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Intro to new Greenland Rising project</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/01/blog-post-IntroToGreenlandRising/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Intro to new Greenland Rising project"/><published>2020-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-01-20T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/01/blog-post-6</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2020/01/blog-post-IntroToGreenlandRising/"><![CDATA[<p>A Collaboration between LDEO (Columbia University, USA) and GINR and Asiaq (Greenland)</p> <h1 id="greenland-rising---predicting-coastal-response-to-changing-ice">Greenland Rising - Predicting Coastal Response to Changing Ice</h1> <p>As ice melts around the world, sea level will rise in many places and fall in some. Because Greenland is very close to the changing ice, the land will rise and sea level will fall, affecting both humans and marine life.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/global_tide_gauge_network.png"/><br/></p> <p>Community responses to changing sea level depend on accurate, location-specific knowledge of the present-day coastal environment and how it is predicted to change. Given the economic, mining, natural resources, and infrastructure development occurring in Greenland there is an urgent need to better understand and communicate the present and future sea level around the island.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/NNA_3systems_austerman.png"/><br/></p> <p>A joint US-Greenlandic team with the new <a href="https://www.nsf.gov/funding/pgm_summ.jsp?pims_id=505594" title="NSF: NNA">NSF project</a> has identified four key Greenlandic communities with different infrastructure that will experience different future sea levels. With a particular focus on these four communities this project will develop better models of how Greenland will rise and the sea level change, as well as mapping shallow water environments to determine what habitats and coastal routes will shift. Together these new predictions of future sea level change and mapping of seafloor habitats will improve the Greenlandic communities’ capacity to respond. This integrated approach will serve as a template for developing a strategy for communities to respond to the changing ice in the Arctic and around the globe.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/GIA_cartoon.png"/><br/></p> <p>Sea level changes throughout the Arctic will be the combined response of the solid Earth (uplift or subsidence) and gravity field to changes in past, present, and future glaciers and ice sheets. Due to the adjacent ice sheet, the signals of shallow water change in Greenland will be large - the Greenland GPS Network (GNET) has documented uplift rates up to 23 mm/yr and subsidence rates of 5 mm/year in the southwest.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/NNA_four_communities.png"/><br/></p> <p>The goal of the Greenland Rising project is to bring together a convergent team focusing for the first time on the natural, social, and built environment of four different Arctic communities proximal to a changing ice sheet. With a focus on these four communities, the team will i) use state of the art technologies to map shallow water environment and habitats ii) develop data-informed models and projections of how sea level has responded to changing ice in the past, present and future and iii) partner with local communities in both collecting the data needed to improve the sea level models and the baseline bathymetric mapping to identify hot spots for future change where new infrastructure, fisheries, and other marine use will be susceptible to change.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Greenland"/><category term="Sea level rise"/><category term="community engagement"/><category term="Ice sheet change"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A Collaboration between LDEO (Columbia University, USA) and GINR and Asiaq (Greenland)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Final year of collecting airborne gravity data with NASA OIB</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/11/blog-post-NASA_OIB-inthefield/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Final year of collecting airborne gravity data with NASA OIB"/><published>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-11-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/11/blog-post-5</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/11/blog-post-NASA_OIB-inthefield/"><![CDATA[<p><br/><img src="/assets/img/NASA_GV_hobart.png"/><br/> (The NASA Gulfstream V (tail N95) on the apron at Hobart International Airport, Tasmania, Australia)</p> <h1 id="flying-low-over-antarctic-ice-shelves-on-a-gulfstream-v">Flying low over Antarctic ice shelves on a Gulfstream V</h1> <p>Final year of collecting airborne gravity data with NASA OIB</p> <hr/> <p>The Operation IceBridge (OIB) mission is in it’s final year, and so far the team, aircraft, and instruments are all working like clockwork, something which might be expected after 10 years of nearly continuous deployments and tests spanning from Alaska to Greenland and down to Antarctica.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/FINAL_OIB - Monday_bagels_vCDL_IntroToHobart.png"/><br/></p> <p>For the firs time OIB will be based out of Tasmania, allowing the Gulfstream V (GV) to reach crucial, yet mostly unmapped, glaciers and ice shelves in East Antarctica.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/FINAL_OIB - Monday_bagels_vCDL_pics.png"/><br/></p> <p>The LDEO Gravity team, which will install and support the operations of two separate airborne gravimeters on the GV include Principle Investigator (PI, the science lead) Kirsty Tinto, myself (Dave Porter, leading hardware and meter operation), Renata Constantino (postdoc working on gravity inversions for bathymetry beneath ice shelves), and Caitlin Locke (leading the processing and quality control).</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/FINAL_OIB - Monday_bagels_vCDL_CookNinnis.png"/><br/></p> <p>Missions lasted up to 10 hours, the safe endurance time for the weight and passenger numbers we require. Flying high and fast (&gt; 40,000 ft), the transit to Antarctica takes at least 2.5 hours. This means allows for up to 5 hours of survey time depending on the sector, which is a considerable amount of new data. Shown in one example of a flight track, plotted over the speed of glacier ice (rainbow colors). This particular mission, Cook-Ninnis, includes flying over its namesake ice shelves and glaciers, collecting crucial gravity and radar data for use in bathymetry inversions.</p> <p><br/><img src="/assets/img/NASA_OIB_ANT-2019_FullGravity_CSYMBmap.png"/><br/></p> <p>At the end of the 5+ weeks of surveying whenever weather and crew rest allowed, this is all the new gravity data collected aboard the GV. Note that we run the gravimeters during transit, since ‘high-and-fast’ gravity data is still useful to many communities. Looking at this map and all the new data collected, it’s clear that this final OIB season was a huge success.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="NASA"/><category term="Antarctica"/><category term="Aerogeophysics"/><category term="Airborne Gravimetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(The NASA Gulfstream V (tail N95) on the apron at Hobart International Airport, Tasmania, Australia)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 2: Integrating the Lamont Gravimeter with the NASA Gulfstream V</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/10/blog-post-NASA_OIB-part2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 2: Integrating the Lamont Gravimeter with the NASA Gulfstream V"/><published>2019-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-17T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/10/blog-post-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/10/blog-post-NASA_OIB-part2/"><![CDATA[<p><br/><img src="/assets/img/20191108_060235.jpg"/><br/> (the NASA Gulfstream V, outfitted with aerogephysical instruments to map the ice sheets. Credit: David Porter, LDEO)</p> <h1 id="part-2-outfitting-an-ex-corporate-jet-for-airborne-science">Part 2, Outfitting an Ex-corporate Jet for Airborne Science</h1> <h2 id="at-nasa-johnson-space-flight-center-in-houston-tx">At NASA Johnson Space Flight Center in Houston, TX</h2> <p>After a few delays, Ryan and I arrive in hot and muggy Houston, finding our crates and large boxes already in the hangar and ready to be unpacked so we can build them up again. A few modifications are needed to be made to the rack after inspection by engineers at NASA, each with their own expertise and eye on a specific aspect of each team’s instrument.</p> <p>After each of the three teams have integrated their equipment on the Gulfstream V, each team needs to test their equipment under a range of flight conditions. These are designed to be progressively more rigorous, in terms of stresses and possible scenarios. Since this every team has flown with NASA OIB in the past, there are several of these tests that work like clockwork and the boxes can be ticked off quickly. However, being on a new type of aircraft this year (in the past we have used NASA DC-8, P3, and C-130), working with a new NASA Space Center (Johnson this year, Armstrong and Wallops in the past), as well as constant upgrading of each instrument team to extend their capabilities, improve reliabilitity, and reduce uncertaintlies, means that issues always crop up. Flying the “shakedown” flight at home, where we have access to the right parts, tools, and NASA expertise, means that fixes are quicker and better when discovered before we get into the field.</p> <p>For 2019 Antarctic season, the radar team from University of Kansas <a href="https://www.cresis.ku.edu/" title="KU: CReSIS">CReSIS</a>, needed several high roll maneuvers for side-lobe characterization. These flight conditions are useless, and actually potentially damaging, for the Lamont Gravimeter Suite, so we kept our system off. On the other hand, the laser team <a href="https://airbornescience.nasa.gov/instrument/ATM" title="NASA: ATM">ATM</a> needs are similar, so we combined out shakedown segments into a single flight. For gravity, we want a straght and level segment as long as we can (at least 15 km) crossing a geological gradient at 90-degrees to the flight direction.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="NASA"/><category term="Antarctica"/><category term="Aerogeophysics"/><category term="Airborne Gravimetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(the NASA Gulfstream V, outfitted with aerogephysical instruments to map the ice sheets. Credit: David Porter, LDEO)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Part 1: Integrating the Lamont Gravimeter with the NASA Gulfstream V</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/10/blog-post-NASA_OIB-part1/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Part 1: Integrating the Lamont Gravimeter with the NASA Gulfstream V"/><published>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/10/blog-post-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/10/blog-post-NASA_OIB-part1/"><![CDATA[<p>Integrating the Lamont Gravimeter Suite with the NASA Gulfstream V</p> <h1 id="outfitting-an-ex-corporate-jet-for-airborne-science-part-1">Outfitting an Ex-corporate Jet for Airborne Science, Part 1</h1> <h2 id="building-up-the-payload-at-lamont-doherty">Building up the payload at Lamont-Doherty</h2> <p>After being awarded the exciting opportunity of being on the Instrument Team for the 2019 Antarctic season with NASA Operation IceBridge, the next steps are to get the scientific instruments built up, tested, and in their flight-ready configurations. In this case, we are flying two gravimeters that have only been flown as separate, independent systems in the past. Because the Gulfstream V (or “GV” as we say) is much smaller than the aircraft we’ve used in the past, with the exception of the British Antarctic Survey’s Twin Otter, we only have one rack worth of space to work with. This is mear 24” by 22” of floor area. However, because we are mapping entirely new terrain, final processing of gravitational anomalies are greatly enhanced when we fly both the force-feedback DGS system and the “strap-down” iMAR system.</p> <p>The challenge associated with combining both gravimeters into a single rack boils down to two simple matters: space and power. For space, we found a solution - the GV rack is slightly taller, and combined with some clever repositioning ideas by Ryan Harris our mechanical engineer, we we able to fit both the iMAR and DGS into a single rack. For power, testing revealed that our new universal power supply (UPS) would provide enough power to both meters, including during the power drop-outs and handovers.</p> <p>The final step is to pack up the systems themselves, the sensors encased safely in LOTS of foam, and all the tools and spares and accessories we can hope to need. Altogether, we shipped 5 boxes totaling</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="NASA"/><category term="Antarctica"/><category term="Aerogeophysics"/><category term="Airborne Gravimetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Integrating the Lamont Gravimeter Suite with the NASA Gulfstream V]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Robots Roaming in Antarctic Waters Reveal Why Ross Ice Shelf Melts Rapidly in Summer</title><link href="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/03/blog-post-2_jgroceans/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robots Roaming in Antarctic Waters Reveal Why Ross Ice Shelf Melts Rapidly in Summer"/><published>2019-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2019-07-22T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/03/blog-post-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://porterdf.github.io/posts/2019/03/blog-post-2_jgroceans/"><![CDATA[<p><br/><img src="/assets/img/ross-ice-front_fromLC130.jpg"/><br/> (The front of the Ross Ice Shelf, as seen from a ski-equipped NY ANG LC-130. Credit: David Porter, LDEO)</p> <h1 id="robots-roaming-in-antarctic-waters-reveal-why-ross-ice-shelf-melts-rapidly-in-summer">Robots Roaming in Antarctic Waters Reveal Why Ross Ice Shelf Melts Rapidly in Summer</h1> <p>A new paper offers fresh insight into the forces causing the world’s largest ice shelf to melt.</p> <p>The Ross Ice Shelf, a part of the Antarctic Ice Sheet that is floating on the ocean, measures several hundred meters thick and sits over 480,000 square kilometers, approximately the size of Spain. Its magnitude, and the fact that thinning of the ice shelf will speed up the flow of Antarctica’s ice sheets into the ocean, mean that it carries significant sea level rise potential if it were to melt. Melting ice shelves like the Ross could cause seas to rise by several feet over the next few centuries.</p> <p>A study <a href="https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1029/2018JC014683" title="JGR: Oceans">just published</a> in the Journal of Geophysical Research: Oceans helps to reveal the local factors that influence the Ross Ice Shelf’s stability, refining predictions of how it will change and influence sea rise in the future.</p> <p>Prior studies on ice shelf melt have focused on warming global waters. Yet three years of Rosetta data show that the Ross Ice Shelf is melting due to local surface waters, and that the melt is happening on an unanticipated part of the shelf. These discoveries were released in a Rosetta paper <a href="https://blogs.ei.columbia.edu/2019/05/27/rosetta-ross-ice-shelf-melting/" title="Tinto Et Al., 2019, Nat. Geo.">published in May</a>; the new study details the source of this strange activity.</p> <p>The study comes out of the Rosetta-Ice project, a three-year-long collection of geologic, oceanographic, and glaciological data in Antarctica. The project is immense in scope, involving a multi-institutional, interdisciplinary team with specialized instrumentation to collect first-of-its kind Antarctic data.</p> <hr/> <p>excerpt from Earth Institute’s State of the Planet <a href="https://blogs.ei.columbia.edu/2019/07/22/ross-ice-shelf-summer-melting/" title="blog post">blog post</a> by Nicole DeRoberts</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="{&quot;JGR&quot;=&gt;&quot;Oceans&quot;}"/><category term="Antarctica"/><category term="publication"/><category term="autonomous ocean profilers"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[(The front of the Ross Ice Shelf, as seen from a ski-equipped NY ANG LC-130. Credit: David Porter, LDEO)]]></summary></entry></feed>